The Somerset Pain Management Service is using a digital health system
to enable patients to manage their long term pain.
The system has beed developed by 'Know Your Own Health'
or 'KYOH' for short.
KYOH is an online system of self-management support:
- information on the health condition
- personalised self-management support
-telephone mentors and on-line peer support
Hi to all and anyone out there.
I've been managing back pain since April 22nd 2011.
I've gone from being totally immobilised with severe pain
to being able to go to the gym, walk a good distance,
do most household chores.
though I find hoovering painful and let my girlfriend mow the lawn!
I get a lot out of talking to people in similar states
so welcome the communication.
I value a positive mental attitude
which is reflected in taking positive action.
I hate dependence on medication or the doctor.
In England, there are more than 15 million people living with
a long term condition
and a good percentage of those people are living with
multiple long term conditions.
Those people only work with health services
on average for between 3 and 7 hours a year.
What we decided to do was to become
a service that saw people and worked with them to support them
to manage their pain in between appointments with us.
When the pain management clinic meetings had finished,
if there had been nothing left,
"that's it, off you go then..."
"yeah, you're going to have pain for the rest of your life"
"we haven't got the resources to deal with you!"
That would have been very threatening actually.
Know Your Own Health is really about
bringing together all of the things that can support you
putting you in control
and enabling you to have sensible, shared
decision-making processes with your healthcare professional.
The first thing I was interested in when I first logged on
was the trackers and the goals.
Although I had a whole raft of self help techniques
they were a bit unstructured.
The trackers I've got are my mood, activities and pain.
so with the activities section, you've got ordinary everyday activities
moving up to intense exercise.
that was very useful for me
to keep a record of the sort of exercise I was doing
and how that related to the pain.
Initially I was monitoring them just to see what
the correlation between my moods and activity etc was
in relation to the pain
but it became really clear very quickly
that mood was playing a massive part in it.
You can add trackers of course.
You could put in your diet.
Or how much alcohol I'm drinking.
How much is that going to affect my pain?
There have been days where I've let it slide,
if someone in the community is logging on and registering that,
I might get a little, "Hey, where are you?"
"You haven't been doing this for a couple of days!"
and it's like, "...yeah...I know..."
When you're living with pain, or any long term condition,
the one word that describes it most for me is 'lonely'.
You feel completely isolated from your family, your colleagues...
Everybody. Nobody really understands what it's like
to live with constant pain unless you're in that situation.
I certainly felt despair, and hopeless...
I would feel very awkward about complaining about pain.
"I'm a man! I don't do that sort of thing; I don't talk about it!"
But the great thing about KYOH is the community.
Both in terms of communicating with each other
and offering practical tips
but just that,
"Yeah, I understand. I know exactly what you're going through mate."
That's worth it's weight in gold.
I'm sure I could benefit from the support of others
and I guess that most of us could.
Does anyone know any support groups for pain management in Frome?
Those people who have worked with us, who have used KYOH
are becoming experts in their own right
and many of them want to contribute and support other people
who maybe don't even need to see us.
but through working with those people who've worked with us,
and through working with them, through KYOH,
we can start to build that community capability and capacity
to manage pain.
I'm very keen actually,
to be able to pass on what I've learned
and help to educate other people.
I can see that there will be less dependence on doctors
and more self-reliance, and more reliance on the community
which has got to be a good thing.
INNOVATIVE ASPECTS OF THE PROJECT:
Use of digital technology for the care
of people with a long term health condition;
Patients self manage their health condition;
Integration of the health service
with an independent digital service provider.