The Mom'Pelleport association offers after-school care
with an artistic focus for 6 to 11 year olds.
Open until 8pm, the association offers families
more flexibility than most public childcare services.
Mom'Pelleport belongs to the Mom'artre network
comprising 7 associations that all follow the same model.
I set up Mom'artre in 2001, in the 18th district of Paris.
As a single mother, I had to juggle my children, their school and my job.
There wasn't an appropriate solution for the situation
so I decided to set up a project for families in the neighbourhood
and single parents in particular.
The population of this neighbourhood is quite mixed
with a lot of social housing, schools and single parent families.
The idea is to offer after-school care,
from the end of school, tea-break, homework support and artistic activities.
Who is responsible for washing up at your table?
Artistic experience is the essential purpose of our project
for two reasons: the first is about giving all children access to art
the second concerns the employment problems faced by artists.
We created the role of 'artist-workshop coordinator'
to offer them a position in line with their training.
This one is yours.
These artists can either work on a one-off project
or become Môm'artre employees.
We organise and finance training in workshop coordination
leading to an official certificate (BAFA)
and offer a range of courses
to strengthen their employment prospects.
I manage the artists who lead workshops during the week.
And as an artist, I'm in charge of four workshops per week,
including photography, painting, ecology, sign language...
Regular artistic activity
- the children come for 3-4 years at least twice a week -
helps develop skills that are not developed at school
like independence, self-expression, living with others.
So Arthur, what do you have on your planet?
Cars...
In order to make art and culture accessible to everyone,
our fees are adapted to each family's income.
We have ten rates, starting at 10 cents/hour.
For example, two children from a family come twice a week
and their monthly bill is around 4,50 Euros.
Our objective is to offer a service to a wide public
so every two months we organise an art exhibition
to showcase the children's and artists' work.
So all families and residents in the neighbourhood are invited
to get together around art.
I appreciate that the service is adapted to everyone.
It's child focused but
it also involves the neighbourhood through the association network.
It's really about 'popular' education in all its glory.
It's an innovative, interesting and original artistic approach
and it's in my neighbourhood.
Mom'artre provides solutions for a range of groups, by:
Offering after-school care with an artistic orientation for children;
Allowing parents, and in particular single parents,
to reconcile work and family life;
Providing employment opportunities and training for artists;
Fostering social cohesion by opening Mom'artre
to the neighbourhood, its residents and associations.
At present, Mom'artre  comprises 7 associations in Paris, Nantes and Arles.
The network plans to extend its services to more municipalities
creating 3 new associations per year.