The Real Pearl Foundation provides art education
to around 600 Roma and non-Roma children
in 12 settlements in Eastern Hungary.
Classes are provided in local schools
and in a purpose-built art school and community centre.
Working in partnership with the children's families,
the Foundation organises income-generating activities
and has set up a project to tackle fuel poverty.
While working with these children,
we had to acknowledge several basic facts.
One of the most significant was that
the problems of children with multiple disadvantages
would never be solved within the schools.
I think that creativity is an unbelievable thing.
It is crucial for children who face failures in primary school
at home and in every segment of society
to experience success somewhere.
It gives them self-confidence, pride and vision in the future.
The success of the school is a testament to the success of the method.
Our pupils win 500 prizes a year all over the world.
After we had seen how successful
creative activities could be for children,
and how easily it worked with personal development,
it was clear that we should try the same with parents too.
Nora had the idea to copy drawings made by
children attending Real Pearl art school
onto canvas.
They bring us the children’s drawings,
we draw them on the canvas
and then give them to the women who embroider them.
When they are ready they bring them back to us
and we put them on cell phone cases, cushions and bags.
We receive money for the products we have made.
These products can be bought
at the Real Pearl Foundation’s social webshop.
We carry out complex work in which self-preservation
and the motivation to work
are the two most important principles.
We buy medicines, distribute food donations,
make bio-briquettes for heating in the winter.
We row them on these strings with an iron nail.
And we put these small sticks between them,
so that air can circulate and it dries faster.
It is packed and we distribute it
among Roma and Hungarian people
who don’t have firewood.
The Foundation actually
fills the gaps left by 'this' badly working system,
it does a bit of social work,
helps the healthcare system a bit,
gets a bit involved in the work of the authorities, in education…
but we don’t want to keep it this way.
This system does not work well this way.
We would like to become part of the state system.
INNOVATIVE ASPECTS OF THE PROJECT:
Child-centered art education for disadavantaged children,
fostering cognitive skills and personality development;
Artistic activities for children are linked to social work,
community building and income generating activities
with parents (embroidery work sold through social webshop);
Filling the gap left by the state in providing complex solutions
in the most deprived and segregated rural settlements.